Guide to the Oliver P. Jenkins Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Oliver P. Jenkins papers
1869-1930
SC0957
Jenkins, Oliver P., (Oliver Peebles), 1850-1935.
0.75 Linear feet
Papers include personal correspondence, 1891-1928; letters of introduction and reference, 1869-1888; reports of his field trips (primarily on fish), 1885-1904; and published and unpublished addresses, pamphlets, and essays, including one on children’s nature study, circa 1920, and one on a visit to California in 1873.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1965.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Oliver Peebles Jenkins was professor and head of the Department of Physiology and Histology, Hopkins Marine Station, Stanford University (1891-1916; emeritus 1916-1935).
Description of the Collection
Papers include personal correspondence, 1891-1930; letters of introduction and reference, 1869-1888; reports of his field trips (primarily on fish), 1885-1904; and published and unpublished addresses, pamphlets, and essays, including one on children’s nature study, circa 1920, and one on a visit to California in 1873.
Access Terms
Hopkins Marine Station; Jenkins, Oliver P., (Oliver Peebles), 1850-1935.; Stanford University. Department of Physiology and Histology. Faculty.; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; Essays.; Manuscripts (for publication).; Notes.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence (incoming and outgoing), 1888-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, outgoing to Ray Lyman Wilbur re OPJ’s pending resignation, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- University training for high school teachers, minutes from meeting held at Stanford, circa 1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Journal of the U.S. Fish Commission exploring Virginia, Tennessee and South Carolina (hand-written entries), 1888 Jul 28-Sep1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Nature Study 1897 – reprint, advertisements, galleys, illustrations (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Reprints (including one on the Hopkins Seaside Laboratory), 1893-1901 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Mexican research trip documents, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence regarding research trip to Hawaii, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Field investigations: fishes collected in Vigo County in 1885-86 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Field investigations: Virginia, Tennessee and North Carolina 1888, and Indiana 1887 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Field investigations: interval between sounds of astronomical clocks, DePaugh University, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Field investigations: amelids breeding during July at Pacific Grove, circa 1896 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Field investigations: exploration of Columbia River to locate hatchery sites for Golden Trout, circa 1904 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 14)
  “Sailor Spiders on Lake Maxinkuckee”; “The Campus Sickle Bills: Bird Life on the Stanford Campus,” 1920; “In considering the Question of Science as Formal Discipline,” undated; [The History of Medical Education in the United States] undated; and “What constitutes Leadership,” undated
- Untitled manuscript on children’s nature study, circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- Typewritten draft of essay on children’s nature study (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
- Research notes, possibly for children’s nature study (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Essays, unidentified (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Address: "Life," Washburn School Address, 1909 Jun 16 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Address: “The True Degree Conferred by the College and Its Responsibilities,” University of the Pacific, 1910 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Letters of introduction and reference, with a few certificates, 1869-1888 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Biographical and bibliographical information (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Biographical essay about California in 1873 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Webster Dictionary title page and frontispiece, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Topographical map, California, Merced County, Planada Quadrangle, circa 1915 (Box 2, Folder 9)